Mss.B.Ey83
American Philosophical Society
Thomas Campbell Eyton correspondence, 1836-1874
Mss.B.Ey83
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Linear feet Ca. 325 items
These letters cover subjects in natural history, especially birds and mollusks.
Ca. 325 items.
Eyton, Thomas Campbell, 1809-1880
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased and accessioned, 1955 (1955 1637-8ms).
General note
This collection was originally compiled for its value as a group of autograph letters.
Biographical/Historical note
Thomas Campbell Eyton (1809-1880) was a British naturalist and agriculturist. While he also studied cattle, and fishes, Eyton is particularly well-known as an ornithologist. His most important work focused on ducks. Eyton was a friend and correspondent of many eminent naturalists of his day, including Charles Darwin (1809-1882, APS 1869), John Gould (1804-1881), Louis Agassiz (1807-1873, APS 1843), Alfred Russel Wallace (1823-1913, APS 1873), Richard Owen (1804-1892, APS 1845), and Sir William Jardine (1800-1874, APS 1845).
Eyton was born in Eyton Hall, near Wellington, Shropshire. His parents were Thomas Eyton, recorder of Wenlock, and later High Sheriff of Shropshire, and his wife Elizabeth. He studied at St. John’s College, Cambridge, but did not take a degree.
Eyton published his first significant ornithological studies in the 1830s. The first two, issued in 1836 and illustrated with elaborate woodcuts, were a History of the Rarer British Birds and Catalogue of British Birds. Two years later followed a book on ducks. Eyton named several birds himself, including the Dendrocygna eytoni, the plumed whistling duck from Australia, which is also called Eyton's tree duck. Several fellow ornithologists, such as Philip Lutley Sclater, the first editor of the ornithological journal Ibis, honored Eyton by naming birds after him. One example is a Brazilian woodcreeper ( Xiphorhynchus guttatus eytoni).
In 1855 Eyton inherited his father’s estate, Eyton Hall. He expanded the manor house to found a large natural history museum. His collection of skins and skeletons of a great variety of birds was the finest of its kind in Europe. The illustrations in his large ornithological study Ostealogia Avium, published between 1871 and 1888, were based on the skeletons in his museum. Eyton prepared many of the specimens himself, and also catalogued the drawings, engravings and portraits in the museum. The collections were dispersed after Eyton’s death; many of them eventually came into the possession of the Natural History Museum at Tring in London, the Liverpool Museum, Cambridge University Museum of Zoology, and the Academy of Natural Sciences in Philadelphia.
Eyton’s research interests extended beyond the study of birds. In 1858 Eyton’s friend Charles Darwin admiringly commented in a letter to him about the “splendid collection of skeletons you have, & how many good irons you have in the fire, for I see that you are, also, going to publish a Book on the Oyster.” Eyton’s study of oysters, published in 1858, was based on his research of the oyster fisheries of the British islands. His other “irons in the fire” included his work in agriculture, more specifically, livestock. He was particularly concerned about improving the Hereford cattle breed. From 1842 to 1860, he published the Herd Book of Hereford cattle which has been used, since its closing in 1886, to preserve the purity of the breed. An avid hunter and sportsman, he also wrote about fishing and fox-hunting. Finally, he published essays about ozone and scent (1870). Eyton was also an active magistrate in his home town of Wellington, and in 1859 he joined the yeomanry cavalry of Shropshire, a volunteer movement that was formed in response to the threat of invasion by France.
Throughout his life, Eyton was generous with support and advice for fellow naturalists, even when he disagreed with their conclusions. For example, Darwin frequently asked Eyton for his advice on matters relating to animals that Eyton had studied. Eyton happily complied by sending information and specimen to his friend. He also helped Darwin prepare descriptions of the birds that were collected on the Beagle voyage. However, Eyton was not pleased to see that Darwin used some of his own observations on the habits of pigeons in support of the hypothesis of natural selection, which Eyton largely rejected. Indeed, Darwin knew that Eyton would not agree with Origins; in 1859 Darwin wrote to his friend in a letter that the “Book will horrify & disgust you.” Nevertheless, their friendship, which dated to Darwin’s undergraduate days at Cambridge, continued until Eyton’s death in 1880.
Eyton was married to Elizabeth Frances, a daughter of Robert Aglionby Slaney, who was a Member of Parliament for Shrewsbury. The couple had seven children.
Scope and Contents note
The collection includes c. 300 items dated between 1830 and 1871. The vast majority of it consists of correspondence addressed to Eyton, and almost all of it deals with matters related to the natural sciences, including especially botany and zoology. Eyton’s activities related to collecting specimens, including shells, is well-documented. Overall, the collection provides insight into the network of information that existed among mid-nineteenth century scientists in Britain, Continental Europe, and, to a more limited extent, North America. The letters are in English, French and German. A typed table of contents is included.
Many of the letters serve as evidence for Eyton’s far-reaching contacts with fellow scientists as well as their practice of exchanging information and natural science specimens. For example, a letter from Raddon thanks Eyton for the insects Eyton sent (1838), one from Yarrell asks Eyton for an egg of the Bernacle (1839), and Walcott thanks Eyton for the box of beetles he sent (1840), and later promises to return the box filled with shells (1841). Walcott refers to the many gifts of insects from Eyton “without being able to make a suitable return” (1850). Numerous additional letters thank Eyton for objects he sent, while others, including one by Houghton (1860) ask him for books and information on certain subjects. Eyton’s contacts with scientists outside of England are reflected in a number of letters, including the letter from Schroeder van der Kolk from St. Petersburg (1844), and a letter by Johann Jakob Haeckel that refers to the possibility of returning a number of specimens if they proved to be not useable for the collections of the Natural History Museum in Vienna (in German, 1850).
Many of the letters that deal with collecting practices were written by or to Hugh Cuming, a naturalist and avid collector of specimens whose collections were eventually purchased by the British Museum. These records shed light on the kind of objects Cuming ordered for himself and others, who supplied him, and how much he paid for them. Examples from this group of material include a note of payment from Sowerby (1849), a letter by Richard Owen (“you are not a man of 2 prices”) (1848), and Lord Derby’s letter that deals with a shipment of birds (1848). Several letters refer to orders of specimens from locations outside of England. Examples are C. B. Adams’ order of shipments to himself and other in the United States (1850), William Dunker’s letter about several shipments of objects from Cassel, Germany (1853), Nappa’s letter from Manila that mentions the preparation of a large collection for Cuming (1855), and a letter by Dr. Klotzsch, the director of the Royal Herbarium in Berlin, about a bill he claimed had been paid (1857). Also of interest is a printed inventory of “Fossil Fish in the Collections of the Earl of Enniskillen and Sir Philip Grey Egerton,” which was sent to Eyton by Egerton in 1841. Similarly, the “Pass for the Derby Museum” lists the number of specimens in its collection (1853). Beginning in the mid-1860s, some of the letters reflect Eyton’s efforts to sell his collection. For example, in 1865 the British Museum was unable to acquire his specimens not so much for lack of funds but because of limited space (letter from Owen), and in 1867 The Royal College also rejected his offer of his collection (letter from Flower). Other notes inquire about the possibility of purchasing some of Eyton’s specimens, including the letter by Sharpe on behalf of the Zoological Society (1870). Also written in the 1860s are a number of letters by various societies and libraries that thank Eyton for his donations of books.
The collection contains many references to fellow scientists and their work. For example, a letter from Jenyns informs Eyton of the fish that Darwin had collected and given to “our society” (1837). News about William Chapman Hewitson is reported in the letter from Yarrell (1839); Derby informs Eyton of Fraser’s return from an expedition (1850); and Wilson writes about the collecting expeditions of Bates and Hawkswell (1850). Strickland notes that his classes at Oxford “consisted chiefly of members of the fair sex,” which he admitted “in order to fill up the unsightly gaps which existed on the benches” (1850). Strickland mentions in a letter to Eyton that his wife’s sickness has prevented her from making the lithographs for his book on birds, and that her sister has done a few plates instead (1852). A few items include more candid information, such as a letter by Adam White that notes Macgillivray’s “unfortunate disposition to take stimulants” (1858).
Eyton was particularly well-known for his illustrated publications. A few letters shed light on matters related to producing, illustrating, and selling his books, including several by William Jardine and Strickland. In one letter, Wilson laments the making of “the fat old Dodo into a Pidgeon,” and wonders what kind of illustrations must by published that “astonish the rising generation” (1850). Two letters were written by the artist Erxleben who illustrated Eyton’s book on skeletons (1858). In a letter to Eyton Richard Owen notes that “You have not only a good artist in Erxleben but a right good man, who has kept himself impoverished by his liberal help to poorer countrymen” (1858). Finally, one letter announces the decision by Edwin J. Prince to accept Eyton’s invitation to serve as London agent for his books (1858).
Ball, Robert, -- 1802-1857.; Bell, Thomas, 1792-1880; Blyth, Edward, 1810-1873; Bree, Charles Robert, 1811-1886; Buckland, Francis T., (Francis Trevelyan), 1826-1880; Crelle, A. L., (August Leopold), 1780-1855; Cuming, Hugh, 1791-1865; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882; Egerton, Philip de Malpas, Sir, 1806-1881; Flower, William Henry, 1831-1899; Forbes, Edward, 1815-1854; Gould, John, 1804-1881; Gray, George Robert, 1808-1872; Gray, John Edward, 1800-1875; Günther, Albert C. L. G., (Albert Carl Ludwig Gotthilf), 1830-1914; Henslow, J. S. (John Stevens), 1796-1861; Hooker, William Jackson, Sir, 1785-1865; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874; Leighton, William Allport, 1805-1889; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892; Patterson, Robert, 1802-1872; Sclater, Philip Lutley, 1829-1913; Strickland, H. E., (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853; Wallace, Alfred Russel, 1823-1913; Yarnell, William, 1784-1856; Birds.; Mollusks.; Natural history.
- Correspondence
  - Letter to Thomas C. Eyton, August 19, 1830; Murray, Andrew, 1812-1878
    Scope and Contents note
    Thanks for insects from North America of which he has few.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, March 26, 1836; 9x7-1/2; Leighton, William Allport, 1805-1889
    Shrewsbury, A.L.S. 4p.,add. Concerning botany.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Shropshire, March 3, 1837; 9x7-1/2; Jenyns, L
    Newmarket, A.L.S. 4p.and add. Concerning fishes. Refers to Darwin and Jardine.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], July 10, 1837; 10x8; Walcott, William H L
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerning insects and shells.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Feb. 12, 1838; 9x7; Raddon, W. (William), 19th cent.
    Bristol, A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning insects.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Dec. 8, 1838; 10x8; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874
    A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning birds and fish. Refers to Gould.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Shropshire, April 26, 1839; 10x8; Yarrell, William, ca.1784-1856.
    A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning birds. Refers to William Chapman Hewitson and Lord Derby.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, May 10, 1839; 9x7-1/2; Leighton, William Allport, 1805-1889
    Shrewsbury, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning botany.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], July 3, 1839; 9x7; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerning natural history.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Aug. 3, 1839; 9x7-1/2; Ball, Robert, 1802-1857.
    Dublin, A.L.S. 2p. Friendly Letter.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], July 23, 1840; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Walcott, William H L
    A.L.S. 3p. Concerning insects and shells.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Sept. 25, 1840; 9x7-1/2; Gould, John, 1804-1881
    London, A.L.S 4p. Forwards skeletons. Concerning birds.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Sept. 30, 1840; 9x7-1/2; Gould, John, 1804-1881
    London, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning natural history and birds. Concerning skeletons.
  - Fossil Fish in the Collections of the Earl of Enniskillen and Sir Philip Grey Egerton, April 23, 1841; Egerton, Philip de Malpas, Sir, 1806-1881
    Scope and Content note
    An inventory list that was sent to Eyton by Sir Egerton.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Aug. 3, 1841; 10x8; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874
    A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning birds. Friendly letter. Refers to Horsfield.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Sept. 24, 1841; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Walcott, William H L
    Bristol, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning insects and shells.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, London, Sept. 15, 1843; 10-1/2x8; Lovén, Sven Ludvig, 1809-1895
    Stockholm, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning shells. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Hugh Cuming, London, April, 1844; 8x4-1/2; Richter, Alexandre
    A.L.S. 3p.and add. In French. Concerning plants and insects. Refers to Reeve and Sowerby.
  - Letter to [Hugh Cuming], Oct. 12, 1844; 9-1/2x8; Schroeder van der Kolk, J. L. C. (Jacobus Lodewijk Conradus), 1797-1862
    St. Petersburg, A.L.S. 1p. Returns boxes of shells and birds. Refers to Strickland and Gray.
  - Letter to [Hugh Cuming], July 6/18, 1845; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Fischer, F E L
    St. Petersburg, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning plants. Sends money for Bridges.
  - Letter to Thomas C. Eyton, July 23, 1846; 7x4-1/2; Walcott, William H L
    Clifton, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning insects and mollusks.
  - Letter to [Hugh] Cuming, Aug. 30, 1846; 10-1/2x8; Fries, Elias Magnus, 1794-1878
    Upsala, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In Latin. Concerning publications. Botany. Refers to Charles Babington.
  - Letter to Thomas G.[sic] Eyton, London, Dec. 31, 1846; 10x8; Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia
    Philadelphia, Printed L.filled in in ms.S.: Walter R. Johnson. 1p.and add. Notifies him of his election to membership.
  - Letter to [Hugh] Cuming, Jan. 2, 1848; 7x4-1/2; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892
    A.L.S. 2p. Business.
  - Letter to [Thomas Campbell Eyton], Feb. 18, 1848; 8-1/2x5; Saueroth, W
    A.L.S. 3p. Business. Informs him of his election to the société de muséum d'histoire naturelle de Strasbourg.
  - Letter to Hugh Cuming, July 4, 1848; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    Concerning shipment of birds.
  - Letter to [Hugh] Cuming, Aug. 18, 1848; 7x4-1/2; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning natural history.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Dec., 1849; 9x7-1/2; Strickland, H. E. (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853
    A.L.S. 3p. Friendly letter. Concerning birds. Refers to Jardine.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, Jan. 8, 1849; 10-1/2x8-1/2; Jonas, D
    Hamburg, A.L.S. 1p. Asks for missing plates from volumes.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, Feb. 14, 1849; 7x4-1/2; Strange, Frederick, 1826-1854
    Port Cooper, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning birds and shells. Refers to F.C.Gray.
  - Letter to Hugh Cuming, March 23, 1849; 6x9; Sowerby,, G. B., (George Brettingham), 1812-1884
    London, A.L.S. 1p.and add. Authorizes payment to his son for shells.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], April 26, 1849; 7x4-1/2; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874
    A.L.S. 3p. Concerning birds. Refers to Reeve.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Oct. 25, 1849; 7x4-1/2; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    Knowsley, A.L.S. 3p. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Jan. 16, 1850; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Blyth, [Edward], 1810-1873.
    Calcutta, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning natural history.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, April 8, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Strickland, H. E. (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853
    Tewksbury, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning skeletons, fossils and birds. Refers to size of upcoming publication. Recommends artist (Mr. G. Ford) to complete illustrations. Refers to Jardine and Gray.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, London, May 6, 1850; 10-1/2x9; Heckel, Johann Jakob, 1790-1857
    Vienna, A.L.S. 1p.and add. Refers to order of fish and other specimen for the Zoological Department of the Natural History Museum in Vienna. In German.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, May 18, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Wilson, Edward
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning birds. Refers to Lucien Bonaparte and Gould.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], May 26, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Fraser, Louis, fl. 1866
    Knowsley, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning the naming of various new species.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, May 28, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    Knowsley, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning fishes. Refers to Fraser and Yarrell. Promises to look out for the kind of fish Eyton wishes to acquire.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], June 12, 1850; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Morelet, Arthur, 1809-1892
    Dijon, A.L.S. 2p. In French. Friendly letter. Refers to Deshayes.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], June 19, 1850; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Leighton, William Allport, 1805-1889
    Shrewsbury, A.L.S. 1p. Asks a favor.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], June 22, 1850; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874
    A.L.S. 6p. Friendly letter. Concerning a publication. Refers to Strickland.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Vineyard, June, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning fishes his fisherman had caught for Eyton. Friendly letter. Refers to Fraser and Sclater.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Aug. 15, 1850; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Wilson, Edward
    A.L.S. 4p.,end. Concerning birds. Friendly letter. Refers to Gould and Lucien Bonaparte.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Aug. 17, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Fraser, Louis, fl. 1866
    Knowsley, A.L.S. 3p. Friendly letter. Mentions Lord Derby and Mr. Haney. Refers to an anticipated appointment.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Aug. 19, 1850; 8x5; Murray, Andrew, 1812-1878
    A.L.S. 3p. Concerning insects.
    General note
    Not located 4/2010.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Aug. 19, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Walcott, William H L
    Clifton, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning insects, including bees. Refers to the Edinburgh Meeting.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, Sept. 26, 1850; 10x8; Adams, C. B. (Charles Baker), 1814-1853
    Amherst, A.L.S. 2p. Friendly letter. Concerning shells. Refers to Gould, Gray, and Redfield.
  - Letter to [Hugh Cuming], Sept. 29/Oct. 11, 1850; 11x8-1/2; Meyer, Charles Antoine, 1795-1855
    St. Petersburg A.L.S. 3p. In French. Concerning plants he had recieved. Forwards money from the St. Petersburg Academy of Sciences. Concerning Fischer.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Oct. 8, 1850; 6-1/2x4; Blyth, [Edward], 1810-1873.
    Calcutta, A.L.S. 4p.,add. Concerning birds. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, Nov. 8, 1850; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Hamilton, William John, 1805-1867
    A.L.S. 2p. Concerning shells. Refers to Sir James Brooke.
  - Letter to Hugh Cuming, Nov. 19, 1850; Magaw
    Plymouth, A.L.S. 1p. Friendly note. Concerning shipment of shells.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, London, Nov. 19, Dec. 3, 1850; 8x5; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    A.L.S. 4p.,add. Concerning shells.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Nov. 30, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Strickland, H. E. (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853
    Tewksbury, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning geology, fossils, and birds. Mentions his classes at Oxford. Refers to Jardine.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Dec. 16, 1850; 7x4-1/2; Strickland, H. E. (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853
    Tewksbury, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning geology and birds. Friendly letter. Refers to Sclater, Jardine and Gould.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Jan. 7, 1851; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Wilson, Edward
    A.L.S. 3p. Concerning birds. Refers to Sclater and Gould.
  - Letter to Thomas C. Eyton, Jan 11, 1851; Fraser, Louis
    A.L.S. 4p.add. About to leave England.
  - Letter to [Thomas C.] Eyton, Jan. 17, 1851; 7x4-1/2; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    Knowsley, A.L.S. 4p. Will be glad to lend specimens. Refers to Fraser.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Feb. 6, 1851; 11-1/2x9; Fenzl, Eduard, 1808-1879
    Vienna, A.L.S. 1p. In French. Botany.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Wellington, Feb. 24, 1851; 7x4-1/2; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    Knowsley, A.L.S. 3p.and add. Friendly letter. Refers to Fraser and Sclater.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], March 17, 1851; 7x4-1/2; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874
    A.L.S. 6p. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Thomas C.] Eyton, Wellington, Feb., 1851?; 7x4-1/2; Derby, Edward George Geoffrey Smith Stanley, Earl of, 1799-1869
    [ca.]. A.L.S. 2p.and add. Sclater may visit his museum. Concerning natural history.
  - Letter to T[homas] C. Eyton, Jan. 6, 1852; 7x4-1/2; Strickland, H. E. (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning birds and fossils. Friendly letter. Refers to Sclater, Wilson, and Jardine.
  - Letter to [Hugh Cuming], June 7, 1852; 11x8; Sallé, Aug., (Auguste), 1820-1896
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. Concerning shells. Mentions orders and books. Refers to Recluz.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Sept. 9, 1852; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Bell, Thomas, 1792-1880
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning birds and mollusks.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, Nov. 4, 1852; 8x5; McAndrews, Robert
    Liverpool, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning shells.
  - Letter to Thomas C. Eyton, Nov 11, 1852; Williams, Thomas
    Thanks Eyton for his generous offer.
  - Letter to Hugh Cuming, Nov. 14, 1852; 10-1/2x8; Eckörth (?), O A
    Copenhagen, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning shells he is sending to Cuming. Requests portrait of Cuming.
  - Letter to [Thomas C.] Eyton, Dec. 29, 1852; 7x4-1/2; Strickland, H. E. (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853
    Tewksbury, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning birds.
  - Letter to [Thomas C.] Eyton, Jan. 16, 1853; 7x4-1/2; Strickland, H. E. (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Feb. 11, 1853; 6x4; Hooker, William Jackson, Sir, 1785-1865
    Kew, A.L.S. 1p. Returns shells.
  - Letter to [Thomas C.] Eyton, April 7, 1853; 6x4; Strickland, H. E. (Hugh Edwin), 1811-1853
    Tewksbury, A.L.S. 3p. Friendly letter. Concerning birds. Refers to Gould.
  - Letter to H[ugh] Cuming, London, April 30, 1853; 10-1/2x8; Hornbeck, H B
    Copenhagen, A.L.S. 1p.and add. Friendly letter. Thanks him for the portrait.
  - Pass for the Derby Museum, May 5, 1853; 3x4-1/2; Moore, Thomas J
    Liverpool, D.S. 1p.
  - Letter to [Hugh] Cuming, June 10, 1853; 8x5-1/2; Bourgengrat, J R
    Paris, A.L.S. 4p. In French. Concerning shells. Refers to Deshayes.
  - Letter to Hugh Cuming, London, June 10, 1853; 10-1/2x8-1/2; Eckörth (?), O A
    Copenhagen, A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning shells, including some he bought at auction for Cuming. Plan to sell his catalogue in England. Business.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], June 17, 1853; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Williams, Thomas
    A.L.S. 1p. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Thomas C. Eyton], Oct. 12, 1853; 7x4-1/2; Jardine, William, Sir, 1800-1874